A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
- V. Policy Analyst Files, 2002-2009 (accession 44690)., Extent: 9.46 cubic feet. (Box 144-169, 173-174)
  - Subseries V.B. Suzette Denslow, Deputy Policy Directory and Legislative Director,2007-2008., Extent: 0.70 cubic feet (Box 148-149)
    - National Association of Retired Federal Employees (NARFE), 2007 (Box 149, Folder 3)
    - Restructuring, 2007 (Box 149, Folder 4)
    - Governor's Awards for the Arts, 2007 (Box 149, Folder 5)
    - Department of Motor Vehicles Financial Issues, undated (Box 149, Folder 6)
    - Immigration, 2007 (Box 149, Folder 7)
    - AARP, 2007 (Box 149, Folder 8)
    - Homestead Exemption, 2007 (Box 149, Folder 9)
    - Pre-K Initiative, 2007-2008 (part one) (Box 149, Folder 10)
    - Pre-K Initiative, 2007-2008 (part two) (Box 149, Folder 11)
    - Pre-K Initiative, 2007-2008 (part three) (Box 149, Folder 12)
    - Pre-K Initiative, 2007-2008 (part four) (Box 149, Folder 13)
  - Subseries V.C. Barbara Reese, Deputy Policy Directory,2009., Extent: 0.70 cubic feet (Box 150-151)
    This subseries is housed in two boxes The original file order has been maintained. Barbara Reese served as Governor Kaine's Deputy Director of Policy from 2009-2010. Reese focused on transportation issues including high-speed rail. On 6 March 2009, Governor Kaine created a Governor's working group, lead by Chief of Staff Wayne Turnage, to evaluate project proposals to be funded by Virginia's allocation from the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009. Kaine appointed Reese to this working group where she focused on infrastructure projects.
    - State of Banking, September 2009 (Box 150, Folder 1)
    - Nice Bridge Meeting, February 2009 (Box 150, Folder 2)
    - High Speed Rail, 2009 (Box 150, Folder 3)
    - Rail Solution, 2009 (Box 150, Folder 4)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part one) (Box 150, Folder 5)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part two) (Box 150, Folder 6)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part three) (Box 150, Folder 7)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part four) (Box 151, Folder 1)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part five) (Box 151, Folder 2)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part six) (Box 151, Folder 3)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part seven) (Box 151, Folder 4)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part eight) (Box 151, Folder 5)
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act Project Idea Submissions, 2009 (part nine) (Box 151, Folder 6)
  - Subseries V.D. Gena Boyle, Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy,2003, 2006-2009., Extent: 5.08 cubic feet (Box 152-166)
    This subseries is housed in 15 boxes and is arranged into three broad topics: Legislative Action Summaries, Subject Files and VIP Letters. The original file order has been maintained. Gena Boyle served as a Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy from January 2006 to December 2009. Boyle focused on agriculture and forestry, health and human resources and natural resources issues. In addition, Boyle coordinated the Governor's response to VIP letters. Proposed responses drafted by an agency or Secretariat were sent to Boyle for Policy Office review and approval (usually by Brian Shepard). The Policy Office would make any necessary changes and forward the draft to Communications. This subseries also contains some records of Maribel Ramos, Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy (2006-2007). Ramos was assigned to the Natural Resources, Administration and Commonwealth secretariats.
    Subjects include: development of land preservation tax credit, Executive Directive 5 - Consumer Data Privacy Work Group, payday lending, Executive Directive 6 - Community Integration, adoption, autism, Governor's Commission on Climate Change, smoking ban in restaurants, foster care, immigration and Virginia Commission on Immigration.
    Notable documents include: Executive Directive 5 Consumer Data Privacy Working Group, 2007 includes meeting notes, agendas and final report to the Governor (b155, f6); Executive Directive 6 Virginia's Comprehensive Cross-Governmental Strategic Plan, draft and final report, 2007 (b155, f16); Briefing on Dominion's Virginia City Hybrid Energy Center (VCHEC), 2008 (b159, f3) and; Bill Review Procedures, 2006 (b165, f2).
    - 2006 Legislative Action Summaries
      - HB 13-HB 173 (Box 152, Folder 1)
      - HB 187-HB 338 (Box 152, Folder 2)
      - HB 346-HB 608 (Box 152, Folder 3)
      - HB 618-HB 852 (Box 152, Folder 4)
      - HB 853-HB 1156 (Box 152, Folder 5)
      - HB 1162-HB 1474 (Box 153, Folder 1)
      - HB 1478-HJ 13 (Box 153, Folder 2)
      - SB 18-SB 176 (Box 153, Folder 3)
      - SB 190-SB 502 (Box 153, Folder 4)
      - SB 534-SJR 4 (Box 153, Folder 5)
    - Subject Files
      - Regulatory Review, 2007 (Box 154, Folder 1)
      - Notes on Governor's Amendments, 2006-2007 (Box 154, Folder 2)
      - Natural Resources Agency Contract Information, 2007 (Box 154, Folder 3)
      - Natural Resources Working Plan, 2007 (Box 154, Folder 4)
      - Roadless Rule, 2006 (Box 154, Folder 5)
      - Virginia League of Conservation Voters (VLCV) and Piedmont Environmental Council (PEC) Survey, 2007 (Box 154, Folder 6)
      - Land Preservation Tax Credit Bill, 2006 (Box 154, Folder 7)
      - Secretary of Natural Resources Memorandums, 2006-2007 (Box 154, Folder 8)
      - Menhaden, 2006 (Box 154, Folder 9)
      - Governor's Natural Resources Leadership Summit, 18-19 September 2006 (Box 154, Folder 10)
      - Payday Loans, 2006-2007 (Box 154, Folder 11)
      - Governor's Sub-Cabinet on Community Design, 2006 (Box 154, Folder 12)
      - Disaster Declaration Requests, 2007 (Box 154, Folder 13)
      - Executive Order 57, Burn Ban, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Food Security Summit Final Report, 11 May 2007 (Box 155, Folder 2)
      - Disaster Declaration: Request for Lee, Russell and Scott Counties, 18 June 2007 (Box 155, Folder 3)
      - Disaster Declaration: Request for Culpeper, Smyth, Washington and Wise Counties, 23 July 2007 (Box 155, Folder 4)
      - Humane Society, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 5)
      - Executive Directive 5, Consumer Data Privacy Working Group, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 6)
      - Nonpoint Source Funding, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 7)
      - Communication with General Assembly, 2007 Session (Box 155, Folder 8)
      - Payday Lending, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 9)
      - Brain Injury, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 10)
      - Joint Subcommittee to Study Liability Protections for Health Care Providers, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 11)
      - Community Action Agencies, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 12)
      - Joint Subcommittee to Study the Medical, Ethical, and Scientific Issues Relating to Stem Cell Research Conducted in the Commonwealth, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 13)
      - Review of the Recovery Experience of Individuals Served at Mental Health Facilities by DMHMRSAS, Office of the Inspector General, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 14)
      - Meeting with Voices for Virginians Children, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 15)
      - Executive Directive 6 (Community Integration Team) Virginia's Comprehensive Cross-Governmental Strategic Plan, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 16)
      - Alliance for Healthier Virginians, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 17)
      - Assisted Living Regulations, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 18)
      - HHR in other states, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 19)
      - Health and Human Resources Information, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 20)
      - AARP, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 21)
      - Virginia Tobacco Settlement Foundation, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 22)
      - State Children's Health Insurance Program (SCHIP) Reauthorization, 2007 (Box 155, Folder 23)
      - Office of the Inspector General, 2007 (Box 156, Folder 1)
      - Special Advisory Commission on Mandated Health Benefits, 2007 (Box 156, Folder 2)
      - Autism Work Group, 2007 (Box 156, Folder 3)
      - Virginia Dept. of Social Services Report on Expediting Adoptions, 2007 (Box 156, Folder 4)
      - Comprehensive Services Act (CSA), 2007 (Box 156, Folder 5)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part one) (Box 156, Folder 6)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part two) (Box 156, Folder 7)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part three) (Box 156, Folder 8)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part four) (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part five) (Box 157, Folder 1)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part six) (Box 157, Folder 2)
      - Health and Human Resources Reports, 2007-2008 (part seven) (Box 157, Folder 3)
      - Health and Human Resources Legislative Studies, 2006-2007 (part one) (Box 157, Folder 4)
      - Health and Human Resources Legislative Studies, 2006-2007 (part two) (Box 157, Folder 5)
      - Health and Human Resources Legislative Studies, 2006-2007 (part three) (Box 157, Folder 6)
      - Health and Human Resources Legislative Studies, 2006-2007 (part four) (Box 157, Folder 7)
      - Joint Commission on Health Care, 2007 (Box 158, Folder 1)
      - Health and Mental Health Care, Potential Budget Initiatives for 2007 Session (part one) (Box 158, Folder 2)
      - Health and Mental Health Care, Potential Budget Initiatives for 2007 Session (part two) (Box 158, Folder 3)
      - Governors' Institute on Community Design, Workshop for Governor Kaine, 15-16 August 2006 (part one) (Box 158, Folder 4)
      - Reference Material, 2007-2008 (Box 158, Folder 5)
      - Reference Material, 2007 (Box 158, Folder 6)
      - Dam Safety Regulations (4 VAC 50-20, 1914/4582), 2008 (Box 159, Folder 1)
      - Blue Crabs, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 2)
      - Dominion Wise County Plant, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 3)
      - Governor's Commission on Climate Change, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 4)
      - 2008 Bill Signings (Box 159, Folder 5)
      - Pending Regulation Issues, 2007-2008 (Box 159, Folder 6)
      - Agriculture and Forestry Economic Impact Study, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 7)
      - Agricultural Champion, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 8)
      - Puppy Mills, 2007 (Box 159, Folder 9)
      - Farm to School, 2007-2008 (Box 159, Folder 10)
      - Guns in State Parks/Forests, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 11)
      - American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy (ACEEE) Virginia Energy Study, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 12)
      - Agriculture and Forestry, Wood to Energy Information, 2007 (Box 159, Folder 13)
      - Ethanol Mandate Waiver Information, 2008 (Box 159, Folder 14)
      - Agriculture and Forestry Trade Issues, 2008-2009 (Box 159, Folder 15)
      - Nature Conservancy Land Conservation Presentation, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 1)
      - Policy and Plan Development Around Chesapeake Bay 2 Year Milestones, 2009 (part one) (Box 160, Folder 2)
      - Policy and Plan Development Around Chesapeake Bay 2 Year Milestones, 2009 (part two) (Box 160, Folder 3)
      - Renew Virginia Initiative Policy Development Documents, 2008 (Box 160, Folder 4)
      - Midwifery, 2008 (Box 160, Folder 5)
      - Dental Clinic for Wise County, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 6)
      - Smoking Ban Research/Meetings, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 7)
      - For Keeps (Foster Care), 2008 Legislative Session (Box 160, Folder 8)
      - Virginia Tech Response Package, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 9)
      - Health Reform Commission, 2007 (Box 160, Folder 10)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration, 2008 (Box 160, Folder 11)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration, 2007 (part one) (Box 161, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration, 2007 (part two) (Box 161, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration Files, 2007 (Box 161, Folder 3)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration Files, 2007 (Box 161, Folder 4)
      - Virginia Commission on Immigration Files, 2007 (Box 161, Folder 5)
      - NGA Conference on Immigrant Integration, 2008 (Box 161, Folder 6)
      - Gena's Cheat Sheets, 2006 (Box 165, Folder 1)
      - Bill Review Procedures, 2006 (Box 165, Folder 2)
      - One Community: Final Report of the Task Force to Develop an Olmstead Plan for Virginia, 28 August 2003 (part one) (Box 165, Folder 3)
      - One Community: Final Report of the Task Force to Develop an Olmstead Plan for Virginia, 28 August 2003 (part two) (Box 165, Folder 4)
      - One Community: Final Report of the Task Force to Develop an Olmstead Plan for Virginia, 28 August 2003 (part three) (Box 165, Folder 5)
      - Joint Commission on Health Care, 9 November 2006 (Box 165, Folder 6)
      - Virginia Division of Child Support Enforcement, The Road to Self-Reliance Starts with Child Support, December 2006 (Powerpoint Presentation) (Box 165, Folder 7)
      - Health and Mental Health Care, Potential Budget Initiatives for 2007 Session (Box 165, Folder 8)
      - Health Care Update, Commonwealth of Virginia, Executive Summary, by Anthem, 2 July 2007 (Box 165, Folder 9)
      - Mental Health, 2007-2008 (Box 165, Folder 10)
      - House Committee on Health, Welfare and Institutions, 10 January 2008 (Box 165, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous Reference Material, 2007-2008 (Box 166, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous Reference Material, undated (Box 166, Folder 2)
    - VIP Letters
      - May 2006 (Box 161, Folder 7)
      - June 2006 (Box 161, Folder 8)
      - July 2006 (Box 161, Folder 9)
      - August 2006 (Box 162, Folder 1)
      - September 2006 (Box 162, Folder 2)
      - October 2006 (part one) (Box 162, Folder 3)
      - October 2006 (part two) (Box 162, Folder 4)
      - November 2006 (part one) (Box 162, Folder 5)
      - November 2006 (part two) (Box 162, Folder 6)
      - December 2006 (Box 163, Folder 1)
      - January 2007 (Box 163, Folder 2)
      - February 2007 (Box 163, Folder 3)
      - March 2007 (part one) (Box 163, Folder 4)
      - March 2007 (part two) (Box 163, Folder 5)
      - June-October 2008 (Box 163, Folder 6)
      - March-May 2008 (Box 164, Folder 1)
      - Natural Resources Letters, 2007-2008 (Box 164, Folder 2)
      - Agriculture and Forestry Letters, 2007 (Box 164, Folder 3)
      - Health and Human Resources Letters, 2007-2008 (Box 164, Folder 4)
  - Subseries V.E. Steven Gould, Senior Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy,2005-2007., Extent: 0.88 cubic feet (Box 167-169)
    This subseries is housed in 3 boxes. The original file order has been maintained. Steven Gould served as Senior Special Assistant to the Governor for Policy from January 2006 to July 2007 when he left the Kaine administration to attend law school. Gould previously worked as Policy Assistant for Governor Mark Warner and some material in this subseries date from that time. During the Kaine administration, Gould focused on agriculture and forestry, commerce and trade, technology, and workforce development issues. He also coordinated the Governor's Fellows program.
    Subjects include: Virginia's petition to the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture for Protection of National Forest System Inventoried Roadless Areas ("roadless rule"), disaster requests to the U.S. Department of Agriculture, development of Governor Kaine's workforce initiatives and 2007 Governor's Fellows applications. The 2007 Governor's Fellows applications contain privacy protected and confidential information and is restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3801 and 2.2-3705.4(2).
    Notable documents include: Petition of the Governor of Virginia to the U.S. Secretary of Agriculture for Protection of National Forest System Inventoried Roadless Areas in the Commonwealth of Virginia, 22 December 2005 (b167, f1); memorandum to Secretary of Natural Resources Tayloe Murphy and Policy Office Director Robert Blue from David Carr, Southern Environmental Law Center, discussing strategy on National Forest Roadless Area Protection in Virginia dated 27 April 2005 (b167, f1) and a similar memorandum to Murphy and Ryan Childress, a policy assistant for Governor Warner, dated 5 October 2005 (b167, f2).
    - "Roadless Rule"
      - "Roadless Rule", 2005-2006 (part one) (Box 167, Folder 1)
      - "Roadless Rule", 2005-2006 (part two) (Box 167, Folder 2)
    - Agriculture
      - U.S. Department of Agriculture Disaster Requests, 2006 (part one) (Box 167, Folder 3)
      - U.S. Department of Agriculture Disaster Requests, 2006 (part two) (Box 167, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Department of Agriculture Disaster Requests, 2007 (Box 167, Folder 5)
    - Workforce Development
      - Career Readiness Certificate, 2006 (Box 167, Folder 6)
      - Governor's Workforce Development Strategic Plan, Steering Committee Resource Book, 2006 (Box 167, Folder 7)
      - Governor's Economic Development and Workforce Development Public Meetings, 2006 (Box 167, Folder 8)
    - Housing
      - Miscellaneous Files, 2006 (Box 167, Folder 9)
    - 2007 Governor's Fellows Program
      - Applications, A-B (Box 168, Folder 1)
      - Applications, B-C (Box 168, Folder 2)
      - Applications, C-G (Box 168, Folder 3)
      - Applications, H-L (Box 168, Folder 4)
      - Applications, L-O (Box 168, Folder 5)
      - Applications, P-S (Box 168, Folder 6)
      - Applications, S-T (Box 169, Folder 1)
      - Applications, T-Y (Box 169, Folder 2)
  - Subseries V.F. Reference Files,2002-2008., Extent: 0.70 cubic feet (Box 173-174)
    This subseries is housed in two boxes. The original file order has been maintained. This subseries contains miscellaneous reference and subject files for the Policy Office. Subjects include: disaster planning, terrorism, and the Jamestown 2007 celebration. Notable documents include: Memorandum from Robert P. Crouch, Jr., Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness to Governor Tim Kaine, dated 10 September 2006, reporting on his 30 August-2 September 2006 Louisiana Hurricane Preparedness Trip (b173, f5).
    - Disaster Planning
      - A Governor's Guide to Emergency Management (Box 173, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Dept. of Emergency Management, Governor's Cabinet Exercise, 15 May 2006 (Participant Handbook) (Box 173, Folder 2)
      - Hurricane Evacuation and Sheltering Task Force, Report to Governor Timothy M. Kaine, August 2006 (copy 1) (Box 173, Folder 3)
      - Hurricane Evacuation and Sheltering Task Force, Report to Governor Timothy M. Kaine, August 2006 (copy two) (Box 173, Folder 4)
      - Louisiana Hurricane Preparedness Trip, 10 September 2006 (Box 173, Folder 5)
      - FluEx'07 Cabinet Tabletop Exercise, 4 September 2007 (Box 173, Folder 6)
    - Terrorism
      - Public Safety Response to Terrorism, Briefing for Governor Mark R. Warner, January 2002 (Box 173, Folder 7)
      - Terrorism and Security Awareness Orientation Instructor Guide, August 2005 (part one) (Box 173, Folder 8)
      - Terrorism and Security Awareness Orientation Instructor Guide, August 2005 (part two) (Box 173, Folder 9)
      - National Capital Region Summit, 12 January 2007 (part one) (Box 173, Folder 10)
      - National Capital Region Summit, 12 January 2007 (part two) (Box 173, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous
      - The Governor's Office Guide, National Governors' Association (part one) (Box 174, Folder 1)
      - The Governor's Office Guide, National Governors' Association (part two) (Box 174, Folder 2)
      - Managing Gubernatorial Records: A Guide for Governors, Council of State Archivists, 2006 (Box 174, Folder 3)
      - The Virginia Transportation Six-Year Improvement Program, Fiscal Years 2006-2011, June 2005 (part one) (Box 174, Folder 4)
      - The Virginia Transportation Six-Year Improvement Program, Fiscal Years 2006-2011, June 2005 (part two) (Box 174, Folder 5)
      - The Virginia Transportation Six-Year Improvement Program, Fiscal Years 2006-2011, June 2005 (part three) (Box 174, Folder 6)
      - Jamestown 2007 Commemoration Update, 11 August 2006 (Box 174, Folder 7)
      - Virginia Sesquicentennial of the American Civil War Commission, Meeting with Brian Shepard, 25 October 2007 (Box 174, Folder 8)
      - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 2008 (Box 174, Folder 8)
      - Richmond Public Library, 2008 (Box 174, Folder 8)